A Guide to the Rodney L. Cool papers, Rockefeller University Faculty FA154
Rockefeller Archive Center
Rodney L. Cool papers, Rockefeller University Faculty
1948-1988, undated
Rockefeller Archive Center
Cool, Rodney L.
FA154
10.6 Cubic Feet
Biographical/Historical note
Rodney L. Cool, 1920-1988. Physicist.
Dr. Rodney L. Cool, an experimental physicist whose research helped to establish the existence of the subatomic particles called quarks, was a professor of high-energy physics at The Rockefeller University.
Born in Platte, South Dakota, on March 8, 1920, Dr. Cool received a B.S. degree from the University of South Dakota in 1942, and an M.A. and Ph. D. from Harvard in 1947 and 1949, respectively. He attained the rank of major in the Army Signal Corps in World War II and was awarded a Bronze Star. He joined the Brookhaven National Laboratory in 1949 as a research physicist and was appointed department chairman of high energy physics in 1960, assistant director in 1964, and associate director in 1966.
In 1970, Cool established an experimental physics group at RU to plan experiments conducted at the European Center for Nuclear Research (CERN), where he also did research. In later years, Cool investigated the detailed properties of the strong force that binds together quarks.
Dr. Cool died on April 16, 1988 of cancer.
Notes: Member-National Academy of Sciences, Fellow-American Physical Society, Chairman-Physics Advisory Committee-FERMILAB Chairman-High Energy Advisory Committee-Brookhaven National Laboratory, Review Committee-Argonne Universities Association, Princeton-Pennsylvania Accelerator Science Committee, Advisory Panel for Physics of the National Science Foundation, High Energy Physics Advisory Panel of the Atomic Energy Commission, Walker Panel Committee on Science and Public Policy-NAS, Associated Universities High Energy Panel-Associated Universities, Inc., Trustee-Universities Research Association, Scientific Associate-CERN, Phi Beta Kappa, Sigma Xi.
Arrangement note
Arrangement by subject.
File Plan note
Former Classification: I 450 C776-U
Conditions Governing Access note
Open for research with select materials restricted as noted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC. Researchers interested in accessing digital media (floppy disks, CDs, DVDs, etc.) or audiovisual material (audio cassettes, VHS, etc.) in this collection must use an access surrogate. The original items may not be accessed because of preservation concerns. To request an access surrogate be made, or if you are unsure if there is an access surrogate, please contact an archivist.
Scope and Contents
Types of records include: correspondence, reprints, notebooks, subject files, project files, and printed material.
Physics; Nuclear physics; Rockefeller University; Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research
- Reprints, 1948-1987; 0.8 Cubic Feet
  Scope and Contents note
  Includes reprints of Cool, Konstantin Goulianos, and other laboratory members.
  Arrangement note
  Arranged in chronological order.
  Scope and Contents
  There is a note in the paper finding aid that there are reprints in box 12.
  - 1948-1962 (Box 1)
  - 1948-1970 (Box 2)
- Correspondence, 1961-1988; 0.4 Cubic Feet
  - General Correspondence, 1961-1971 (Box 2)
    Arranged in chronological order and by subject.
  - Correspondence, 1969-1988 (Box 12)
    Conditions Governing Access
    Restricted from scholarly access.
- Panels & Committees, undated; 3 Cubic Feet
  Includes correspondence, memos, papers, and reports.
  Subjects include AUI High Energy Physics Panel, High Energy Physics Advisory Panel, NAS Panel on Elem. Particle Physics, NASA, NSF Physics Panel, Princeton-Penn Science Committee, and SLAC.
  Arranged in original order.
  - MIT-Physics Progress Reports - Laboratory of Nuclear Science (Box 2)
  - HEPAP - High Energy Physics Advisory Panel, 1969-1971 (Box 3)
  - HEPAP, 1967-1968 (Box 4)
  - NAS - Physics Survey Committee - Panel on Elementary Particle Physics, 1963-1964 (Box 4)
  - AUI - High Energy Physics Panel, 1968 (Box 5)
  - Division of Particles and Fields (Box 5)
  - High Energy Discussion Group (Box 5)
  - NSF - Physics Panel. Northwestern University (Box 5)
  - Princeton-Penn Science Committee (Box 5)
  - Organizing Committee of Particle Physics Society/Advances in High Energy Physics (Box 5)
  - Elas & Incl. Working Papers (Box 5)
  - Carnegie-Mellon University (Box 5)
  - Harvard Visiting Committee (Box 5)
  - NASA (Box 5)
  - SLAC (Box 5)
- CERN (European Center for Nuclear Research), undated; 1 Cubic Feet (Box 6)
- NAL, undated; 1 Cubic Feet (Box 7)
- RU, NSF, BNL, URA, NAS, 1959, undated; 1 Cubic Feet
  - RU, NSF, BNL, URA, NAS, 1959, undated (Box 8)
  - BNL, 1959 (Box 13)
- Notebooks, 1952-1959, undated; 1.6 Cubic Feet
  - Notebooks, 1.6 Cubic Feet (Box 9)
  - Notebooks (Box 10)
  - Notebooks, 1952-1959, undated (Box 12)
  - Notebooks, undated (Box 13)
- Subject Files, undated; 0.3 Cubic Feet (Box 10)
- Conferences and Seminars, undated; 0.5 Cubic Feet (Box 10)
- Project Files; Lecture Notes, 1950-1988, undated; 1 Cubic Feet (Box 11, Box 12)
  Accruals
  Addition 1989 January 12.
- Journal Articles, 1979-1987 (Box 12)
- Correspondence, 1969-1988 (Box 12)